You don't want to be messing around with any other stuff.
You want to have a fire.
Not only does this give you light it gives you warmth but most of all it gives you that personal feeling of safety.
Knowing that you have a fire around you.
To build this you're going to look for some small kindling.
Small dry stuff leafs, pin straw.
Pull some of the interior of your socks out.
Fluff that up to where you can have something.
That you can ignite very easily.
OK, you want to get some really small dry wood.
Then you want to start to collect some bigger stuff.
Some stuff that's going to burn a long time.
Try and look for hard woods verses soft woods oaks, hickory's, maples.
These are going to burn longer and warmer.
So that it'll help you out in the long run.
OK, then you're going to have to find something to ignite it with.
Some people have sparker's a lighter, matches, flint and steel.
If you don't have that you can use two pieces of rock, hard rock.
Most of the time they'll lay a spark just might take a little longer but first off when you do get lost or stranded.
You all ways want to make a fire first.
This'll help you the most in the long run and that's how to build you a speed fire in case you're surviving nature.